<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-16T20:25:34+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Lawrence Borst Blog</title><entry><title type="html">Generalizing graph theory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/complexes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Generalizing graph theory" /><published>2020-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Generalizing%20Graph%20Theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/complexes">&lt;p&gt;Here we will look at a generalization of graph theory. All visualizations were made in Blender3D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to generalize graph theory. One way is with the “hypergraph”, which in essence is a graph where edges can connect to more than $2$ vertices. This is easy to visualize if we imagine edges as being able to “branch”. A bit of imagination can lead us to other generalizations, and here I present one I came up with that motivates the rich theory of CW complexes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Generalizing Finite, Connected Planar Graphs and Euler's Theorem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, let us try to generalize connected simple planar graphs, because they are quite “nice”. Firstly, they are graphs, but they are also fundamentally geometric, as planar graphs are those that can be embedded in the plane. We will extend two theorems: firstly, connected simple planar graphs have the property (Euler’s Theorem) that, if $v$, $e$, $f$ be the number of vertices, edges and faces respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Euler’s Theorem: If a finite, connected planar graph is drawn in the plane without edge intersections, then&lt;/p&gt;

\[v-e+f=2\]

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, planar graphs can be embedded onto the plane without any edges intersecting. In fact, note how neither vertices, edges nor faces intersect other vertices, edges or faces respectively. In fact(!), note how—if we identify vertices as points, edges as lines and faces as bounded open sets filling in the space between edges (polygons)—neither points, edges or faces intersect other points, edges or faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Euler’s Theorem is a little misleading as it stands now because I haven’t quite defined what constitutes a “face”. In particular, for graphs that can be embedded into a bounded subset of the plane, we still take the “outside” of the graph to be counted as a face. We shall see, rather surprisingly, that in the generalization here it is maybe more elegant to say that the “outside” does not constitute a face and that $v-e+f=1$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, there is a lot to be tightly, mathematically formulated. But this is not necessary, because I only want to illustrate the ideas involved in generalizing planar graphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that connected simple planar graphs are, well, planar. That is, they are clearly embedded into the 2D plane, i.e. 2D euclidean space. We might expect a generalization to be 3-dimensional. The obvious generalization is what computer scientists call a polygon mesh, which intuitively can be viewed as a volume whose boundary is a set of poylgons (though this does not rule out pathological cases). Examples are, of course, polyhedra, but also complicated volumes that have been, as they say, triangulated. Indeed we shall go with polygonal meshes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we notice how a polygonal mesh “glues” to another polygonal mesh; it is quite clear it can be glued by a face. Let’s go with that idea, because in the planar graphs we have discussed a face can be glued to a face by an edge, and an edge can be glued to an edge by a vertex. Furthermore, we don’t necessarily disallow gluing faces together by vertices; for this reason we can glue polygonal meshes by vertices, or edges as well. This is very elegant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the sake of brevity, let us call the generalization of a “face” a “room”. The following shape has $1$ room, $4$ faces, $6$ edges and $4$ vertices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SHOW TETRAHEDRON&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following more complicated shape has $2$ rooms, $10$ faces, $15$ edges and $8$ vertices. Note how, when two rooms are glued together, they share a face, not two faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SHOW SECOND SHAPE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let us try to generalize Euler’s formula. We will, for simplicity, disregard the face “outside” the shape, so that for simply connected planar graphs $V-E+F=1$. If a generalization for the planar case exist to higher dimensions, then we might expect the existence also of a “reduction” to lower dimensions. In $d=1$, we have a graph that we may draw on a line. The rules are: (1) we may draw a vertex or an edge and (2) edges and vertices may not intersect other edges and vertices. Furthermore, we shall not take the “outside” part as an edge. The reader can convince him/herself that such graphs satisfy $V-E=1$. If we had taken the “outside” as an edge, we would have $V-E=0$. Now let’s go zero-dimensional. We have a euclidean space that consists of a single point. This point can be the vertex, but no edges can be added (because they are one-dimensional) and no additional vertices (because (1) vertices would intersect and (2) there would be no edges connecting them). Clearly Euler’s formula is then $V=1$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have seen that Euler’s formula for $n=0$, $1$, $2$ is $V=1$, $V-E=1$ and $V-E+F=1$. There is a clear pattern, and let us conjecturet that in 3D $V-E+F-R=1$ where $R$ is the number of “rooms”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the two 3D shapes given, we indeed find that $V-E+F-R=1$ in both cases(!). It seems like we have found a valid generalization of Euler’s formula, and this is indeed the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;cw-complexes&quot;&gt;CW-Complexes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will see that the above discussion ties in very naturally with an accepted generalization of graphs, namely CW-complexes. These are more abstract, topological objects that generalize the hierarchy of vertices, edges, faces and so on, with rules prescribing how they are combined. The complex is then the graph. The definition is particularly simple in the case of finite graphs. CW-complexes are made from $n$-cells, so let’s first define those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definition&lt;/strong&gt;: An $n$-cell is a space homeomorphic to the open $n$-disk $int(D^{n})$. A cell is a space which is an $n$-cell for some $n \geq 0$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we define $D^{n} = \left \{ x : \left | x \right | \leq 1 \right \}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definition&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intuitively the first axiom tells us two things: (1) that each cell can be built from the $n$-disk, should we allow continuously deforming it into $X$, and (2) that the boundary of such a cell is restricted to $X^{n-1}$. The first part intuitively captures the natural progression from points, to curves, to surfaces, to volumes that we have seen in graphs. The second part, based on our previous discussion, says that faces have boundaries that contain vertices and edges, but NOT “rooms”. In graph theory we would naturally not define the boundary of an edge to be a face; it makes much more sense for it to be a vertex. This is captured here. Furthermore, this tacitly embodies the idea that graphs are made from “gluing” together different components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second axiom is more subtle, and rules out pathological cases. The same can be said of the thirrd axiom, and in fact they are superfluous if E is finite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Euler Characteristics&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;</content><author><name>Lawrence Borst</name></author><category term="mathematics" /><category term="math" /><category term="graph" /><category term="theory" /><category term="CW" /><category term="complex" /><category term="complexes" /><summary type="html">Here we will look at a generalization of graph theory. All visualizations were made in Blender3D. There are many ways to generalize graph theory. One way is with the “hypergraph”, which in essence is a graph where edges can connect to more than $2$ vertices. This is easy to visualize if we imagine edges as being able to “branch”. A bit of imagination can lead us to other generalizations, and here I present one I came up with that motivates the rich theory of CW complexes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finding chords in microtonal music part 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/microtonal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding chords in microtonal music part 1" /><published>2020-11-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Finding%20Chords%20in%20Microtonal%20Music%20Part%201</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/microtonal">&lt;p&gt;I see microtonal music as an often dissonant art. This perception owes itself in part to its strangeness, but also to scientific principles that make many types of microtonal music unattractive to the uninitiated. For example, imagine a pitch. Play it in your head, and then layer it with a second pitch just slightly above the first. What you’re hearing is a dissonant interval, and we shall go over the reason why that may be. We will attempt to categorize chords by their “pleasantness” to the ear, and show how this problem can be handled mathematically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before we can dive into microtonality we need to understand Western tuning, how sound is perceived, and what makes a sound pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Octave, Pitches and Sound Waves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good starting point is the octave. The octave is an interval, meaning it denotes a pitch relationship between two notes. The octave is a natural starting point when it comes to tuning. When I play a C4 and a C5 simultaneously on a piano, it will sound harmonious. Perfect. In fact, the C4 and C5 “feel” similar, and musicians may use terms like “perfect octave” to describe such assonant intervals. You could say C5 sounds like a “higher” C4. But when we shift somewhere arbitrary, like E5, we would not say it sounds like a “higher” C4… But we could say it sounds like a higher E4-if you’re human, that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pitch in music is a perceptual property of sound. A sound is a pressure wave, and for a pitched sound, the pressure it carries to your ear will be periodic. A sound wave can be quite arbitrary; pitch will be perceived as long as it is periodic. Your brain is able to distinguish the frequency of sound, and from this frequency perceives a pitch. While we’ll talk a lot about “pitch”, I remind the reader that pitch is only a perception, and the frequency of sound waves is fundamentally where music happens physically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what makes the octave special? It is this: if the “lower” sound has pitch $x$, then the “higher” sound will have pitch $2x$. Precisely $2x$. If we begin to deviate, by playing at say a frequency of $2x+\epsilon$, the resulting interval will sound less harmonious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think we fundamentally know &lt;b&gt;why&lt;/b&gt; our brains favor intervals such as this—in fact, it isn’t even clear if animals have opinions about intervals at all—but it seems to be the way it works. We can, however, make a guess why the two pitches sound “similar”. Maybe it is because a sound with frequency $2x$ necessarily also has frequency $x$. This does, however, not reveal why the magic number is $2$, instead of $3$ or something. (But the brain &lt;b&gt;does&lt;/b&gt; favor sounds at frequencies $x$ and $3x$ played simultaneously. This would be a perfect twelfth, and sounds harmonious, but nothing like duplicating a sound)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Equal Temperament Tuning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shall briefly look at the Western tuning system, because microtonality naturally extends it. Western tuning—in particular what we might call equal temperament—can be constructed from two pieces of information: a reference pitch, and the number of equal intervals we split an octave into. The reference pitch acts like an “origin”, and in Western music we could set it at A4, which we define to be $440$Hz (ocillations/repetitions per second of a sound).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what should A5 be, one octave up? Well, $880$Hz, from the previous discussion. A6? Perhaps it is tempting to bet on $1320=3(440)$, but it is 1760Hz, because the relationship between A6 and A5 is the same between A5 and A4. That is, A6 doubles the frequency associated with A5, the same way A5 doubles that with A4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reader may recognize that when we choose to split the octave into equal intervals, we are forced not to cut the octave into equal frequencies, but rather to pick frequencies in geometric progression. This multiplicative behavior may seem striking, but in a way pitch perception is not much different from how humans perceive many other stimuli (see Steven’s power law). Loudness, touch sensitivity, pitch and warmth perception all follow power laws with respect to our “perceived intensity”. In a sense, pitch and vibrations are related by Steven’s power law. Mathematically it doesn’t really matter if it’s a power law or a linear law… But I digress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if we start with A4 at $440$Hz, what frequency should the next note (Bb4) be? Well, say we wish to split A4 to A5 into twelve equal intervals, and each interval takes us further by a (multiplicative) factor of x. Then, moving up 12 steps (semitones), we get $440x^{12}=880$, giving $x=\sqrt[12]{2}$. Then Bb4 is at $440\sqrt[12]{2}\approx 466.16$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point we can construct all $88$ keys on the keyboard with their associated frequencies. We’ll leave tuning at that for now, though the subject goes much deeper in practice—there are infinite families of tuning systems to draw from! The tuning system here is most commonly used on synthesizers, electric guitars, and keyboard instruments, just to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Mathematics of Consonant Intervals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re nearing the prerequisite knowledge to understand how to tackle microtonality. But to solve the problem of finding pleasant chords in it, we need to understand “consonance” and “dissonance”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where “consonance” conveys something pleasant, “dissonance” conveys something unnerving. This is the same to how “consonance” and “dissonance” are used to talk about intervals. The mathematical machinery of consonant intervals is every bit as harmonious as its sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roughly, when two notes $A$ and $B$ are heard, the “closer” the ratio between their associated frequencies $f(A):f(B)$ is to a rational number of the form $a:b$ with small $a$ and $b$ (coprime), the more harmonious it sounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, $f(A5):f(A4)=2:1$ is very harmonious. This is an the pitch ratio associated with an octave. For a perfect fifth, which is considered the “second-most” consonant interval, we have something like $f(A5):f(E5)=\sqrt[12]{2^{7}}\approx 1.498$ because a perfect fifth has 7 “steps” (semitones). This number is irrational, and so you may expect it to be very dissonant. But it is also awfully close to a “nice rational number”, namely $3:2=1.5$ That is why it sounds “nice”. In fact, we can see that octaves and perfect fifths sound “nice” everywhere on the keyboard, as long as the ratio of frequencies is conserved. We humans are so accustomed to thinking about pitch in this relative way that we are better at distinguishing the interval two notes make than any one note’s exact position! This is called relative pitch. I’ve heard of people with absolute pitch—the perception of pitches as “absolute” frequencies—feeling dumbfounded that most people perceive music in such a complex, roundabout way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how do we characterize “closeness?” I have searched online for this, but couldn’t find any resources. On the internet there are scores of lists with these ratios related to the $12$ intervals we all know and love. But no derivation. I have chosen to show a personal method based on continued fractions. Every number $x\in \mathbb{R}$ can be expressed in the form:&lt;/p&gt;

\[x=a_{0}+\frac{1}{a_{1}+\frac{1}{a_{2}+\frac{1}{\ddots}}}\]

&lt;p&gt;Where $a_{i}\in \mathbb{Q}$. The above expression is the continued fraction expansion of $x$, and we often write $x=\left [ a_{0};a_{1}, a_{2}, a_{3},\cdots  \right ]$. For rational $x$, this expression terminates. Conversely, every terminating continued fraction is rational. For irrational $x$, it doesn’t terminate. We can draw a lot of similarities between continued fraction and decimal expansions… But continued fractions are more powerful. The continued fraction of $x$ is the best approximation to $x$ in the following sense: if $p/q$ (coprime) is any one of those fractions obtained by truncating the full continued fraction, then it is impossible to find $s &amp;lt; q$ in $\mathbb{Z}$ such that $r/s$ is closer to $x$. Furthermore, the error is less than $\frac{1}{q^{2}}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We therefore choose to define the pitch ratio “close” to $x=\left [ a_{0};a_{1}, a_{2}, a_{3},\cdots  \right ]$ as the truncated $\left [ a_{0};a_{1}, a_{2}  \right ]=a_{0}+1/(a_{1}+1/a_{2})$. We could have more terms, of course, but I don’t think this is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s derive the coefficients. I’ll outline the derivation from The Princeton Companion of Mathematics; the trick comes from 13th century Indian and Arabian mathematics, and is based on the Euclidean algorithm. If we pick $m$ and $n$, and find unique quotient and remainder $q_{1}$, $r_{1}$ with $m=q_{1}n+r_{1}$ (constrained in the usual way), then $m/n=q_{1}+r_{1}/n=q_{1}+1/F$, where $F=n/r_{1}$. Using the Euclidean algorithm again, we can write $n=q_{2}r_{1}+r_{2}$, giving $F=q_{2}+r_{2}/r_{1}$. The next step is to produce an expression for $r_{2}/r_{1}$. Doing so indefinitely will produce the infinite fraction expansion in the following form:&lt;/p&gt;

\[x=q_{0}+\frac{1}{q_{1}+\frac{1}{q_{2}+\frac{1}{\ddots}}}\]

&lt;p&gt;Let’s apply this to the perfect fifth. The pitch ratio associated with a perfect fifth is $x=\sqrt[12]{2^{7}}$. The integer part of $x$ is $1$, by inspection. The remainder is roughly $0.4983$, and the reciprocal of that ($F$ in the above) is $2.0068$ with an integer part of $2$. Stopping here gives $3/2$, which is what we want. But we will not stop there, mainly because a diminished sixth is also $3/2$ if we choose to stop here; the diminished sixth should be very dissonant. Instead, going one step furher, we have $F=147$! A large jump. We then find that $x$ is “close” to $442/295$! That sounds terrible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musicians might cringe at this method, because the fraction is so ridiculously complicated where they might expect it to be simpler (because a perfect fifth his consonant). But here we exactly want large fractions. Consider the following expressions:&lt;/p&gt;

\[x=1+\frac{1}{2}\]

\[y=1+\frac{1}{2+\frac{1}{147}}\]

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the expressions, we can tell that they are really close because $1/147$ is close to zero. Furthermore, $x$ is our first “best” approximation to the perfect fifth, and $y$ is our second “best”… And there’s nothing in between that’s better. But that’s saying that a perfect fifth is already very close to $3/2$. This means that the perfect fifth is very close to a “nice” rational number. In fact, we’re kind of measuring the “irrationality” of $\sqrt[12]{2^{7}}$ based on the way expression unfolds. This has been done before, but not in a way that can be usefully applied to music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will now have to define precisely how we’re going to measure how dissonant the intervals are based on these expressions. There’s no one way to do this, but it’s clear that we can take the octave as the most consonant interval by default, and by the irrationality of all the other intervals we can assume $x$ has an infinite expansion, and so we can find the first $n$ terms. Some exhausting hours of work showed me that no clear pattern emerges by just looking at the first $5$ or so terms. For instance, the continued fraction associated with the tritone (besides a minor second, the “ugliest” interval) is $[1; 2, 2, 2, 2…]$. We expect this to be dissonant because all the numbers are rather small. But looking at the minor 6th (quite a “nice” interval) we get $[1, 1, 1, 2, 2…]$. But shouldn’t that be even more dissonant?! All this may be a fool’s errand. Yet I couldn’t find any papers; even the so-called “limit theory” in music (which deals with questionsl like ours) I couldn’t find proper justification for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But looking at a &lt;a href=&quot;http://cc.oulu.fi/~tma/TAPANI28.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferer&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; connecting infinite radicals with a measure of the “irrationality” of a number, I was led to believe that the most important thing is the magnitude of the first fractional term (kept small for consonance), and that of the largest term we’ll encounter after (large for consonance). Indeed, going a bit further, we obtain $[1, 1, 1, 2, 2, 1, 3…]$. I’ve never been this happy to see a $3$!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the tritone corresponds to a pitch ratio of $2^{1/2}$, the “twos” in the expansion never terminate. But looking at the minor sixth, we get a $3$, which is more consonant than $2$… And $12$ terms in—after a long streak of $1$’s, $2$’s and some $3$’s, we get a whopping $30$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, some of these continued fractions converge slooowly. The “Just Noticeable Difference” between pitches is quite precise (it also follows a power law of sorts, namely Weber’s law), so I wanted to investigate the relationship between the different truncations of the continued fractions &lt;b&gt;up to the point&lt;/b&gt; where we can no longer distinguish frequency differences. I also wanted to investigate whether our perception of consonance is related to a point where our brains will decide that the sound can be reasonably approximated by a simple ratio. This would relate to the truncation associated with the first big “jump” in our continued fraction, rather than a set number of iterations. Such a “jump” can definitely be characterized in absolute terms, and this can all be happily investigated. And that is the objective for part II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(To be continued)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lawrence Borst</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="microtonal music" /><category term="chords" /><summary type="html">I see microtonal music as an often dissonant art. This perception owes itself in part to its strangeness, but also to scientific principles that make many types of microtonal music unattractive to the uninitiated. For example, imagine a pitch. Play it in your head, and then layer it with a second pitch just slightly above the first. What you’re hearing is a dissonant interval, and we shall go over the reason why that may be. We will attempt to categorize chords by their “pleasantness” to the ear, and show how this problem can be handled mathematically. But before we can dive into microtonality we need to understand Western tuning, how sound is perceived, and what makes a sound pleasant.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lagrange interpolation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/lagrange-interpolation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lagrange interpolation" /><published>2020-11-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Lagrange%20Interpolation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/lagrange-interpolation">&lt;p&gt;To launch this website, let’s begin with the simple but elegant idea of Lagrange interpolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim is to find a polynomial of degree $n$ that passes through $n-1$ points. People educated in linear algebra often can see that this is possible just by setting up the associated system of linear equations. For completeness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If $P(x)=a_{0}+a_{1}x+\cdots+a_{n}x^{n}$ and $P(x_{0})=y_{0}$, $P(x_{1})=y_{1}$,$\cdots$,$P(x_{n-1})=y_{n-1}$ then we have the following system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

\[y_{0}=a_{0}+a_{1}x_{0}+\cdots+a_{n}x_{0}^{n}\]

\[y_{1}=a_{0}+a_{1}x_{1}+\cdots+a_{n}x_{1}^{n}\]

\[\vdots\]

\[y_{n-1}=a_{0}+a_{1}x_{n-1}+\cdots+a_{n}x_{n-1}^{n}\]

&lt;p&gt;$n$ unknowns and $n$ equations. This we know is solveable. You can solve this by hand for a few points—and a computer will have no trouble with thousands of points—but our aim is to find a closed-form formula for the interpolating polynomial. Looking at this set of equations might not get us anywhere close to solving this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of revealing the trick, I encourage the reader to think about the problem. A good line of reasoning is something like this: “The main difficulty is that when you assume a function $P(x)$ and tweak the coefficients to fit through some point, the polynomial will inevitably slip away from other points.” It is a bit like trying to get rid of a crease on your bedsheets; flattening one part will cause a pinch to pop up elsewhere. So then we might ask ourselves: “Is there a way to treat an individual point without disturbing the rest?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, consider one of the points we’re trying to pass through. If we can associate a polynomial (which is what the question is about) with an individual point that’s “nice” in a way that “does not disturb the others”, we would need a total of $n$ polynomials to address all points. Every polynomial should act in a similar way to its associated point, because no point is “special”. So something should be quite “natural” about this polynomial. It should pass through a point, and as for the others… Well, be equal to $0$ at the others (can you think of anything else?). This is quite a natural thing to do with the other points, and as it turns out, it is easy to find the associated polynomial. Promising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say $P_{i}(x)=0$ at $x=x_{j}$ for all $j \neq i$ and $P_{i}(x_{i})=y_{i}$. By the fundamental theorem of calculus, we have:&lt;/p&gt;

\[P_{i}(x)=C_{i}\prod_{j \neq i} (x - x_{j})\]

&lt;p&gt;For some constant $C_{i}$. Plugging in $P_{i}(x)=y_{i}$ gives $C_{i}=y_{i} / \prod_{j \neq i} (x_{i} - x_{j})$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have tamed the problem in the sense that we can find a polynomial of degree $n-1$ through a given point, that equals $0$ at all the other points. The attempt so far may not lead anywhere—as happens often when you’re tackling a problem for the first time—but some thought reveals that the sum of all these polynomials goes through the points $(y_{0}, x_{0}), (y_{1}, x_{1}),\cdots,(y_{n-1}, x_{n-1})$. Therefore&lt;/p&gt;

\[P(x)=\sum_{i=0}^{n-1}y_{i} \frac{\prod_{j \neq i} (x - x_{j})}{\prod_{j \neq i} (x_{i} - x_{j})}\]

&lt;p&gt;Solves the problem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lawrence Borst</name></author><category term="lagrange polynomials" /><category term="interpolation" /><category term="approximation" /><category term="mathematics" /><category term="math" /><summary type="html">To launch this website, let’s begin with the simple but elegant idea of Lagrange interpolation. The aim is to find a polynomial of degree $n$ that passes through $n-1$ points. People educated in linear algebra often can see that this is possible just by setting up the associated system of linear equations. For completeness: If $P(x)=a_{0}+a_{1}x+\cdots+a_{n}x^{n}$ and $P(x_{0})=y_{0}$, $P(x_{1})=y_{1}$,$\cdots$,$P(x_{n-1})=y_{n-1}$ then we have the following system:</summary></entry></feed>