<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-20T22:08:26+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Lawrence Borst Blog</title><entry><title type="html">Finding chords in microtonal music</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/20/Finding-Chords-in-Microtonal-Music.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding chords in microtonal music" /><published>2020-11-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/20/Finding%20Chords%20in%20Microtonal%20Music</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/20/Finding-Chords-in-Microtonal-Music.html">&lt;p&gt;I see microtonal music as an often dissonant art. This perception owes itself in part to its strangeness, but also to scientific principles that make many types of microtonal music unattractive. For example, imagine a pitch. Play it in your head, and then layer it with a second pitch just slightly above the first. What you’re hearing is a dissonant interval, and we shall go over the reason why that may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Western music is tuned on twelve equal intervals per octave. Before we can dive into microtonality we need to understand what that means, because microtonality generalizes Western tuning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Octave, Pitches and Sound Waves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good starting point is the octave. The octave is an interval, meaning it denotes a pitch relationship between two notes. The octave is a natural starting point when it comes to tuning. When I play a C4 and a C5 simultaneously on a piano, it will sound harmonious. Perfect. In fact, the C4 and C5 “feel” similar, and musicians may use terms like “perfect octave” to describe such assonant intervals. You could say C5 sounds like a “higher” C4. But when we shift somewhere arbitrary, like E5, we would not say it sounds like a “higher” C4… But we could say it sounds like a higher E4-if you’re human, that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pitch in music is a perceptual property of sound. A sound is a pressure wave, and for a pitched sound, the pressure it carries to your ear will be periodic. A sound wave can be quite arbitrary; pitch will be perceived as long as it is periodic. Your brain is able to distinguish the frequency of sound, and from this frequency perceives a pitch. While we’ll talk a lot about “pitch”, I remind the reader that pitch is only a perception, and the frequency of sound waves is fundamentally where music happens physically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what makes the octave special? It is this: if the “lower” sound has pitch $x$, then the “higher” sound will have pitch $2x$. Precisely $2x$. If we begin to deviate, by playing at say a frequency of $2x+\epsilon$, the resulting interval will sound less harmonious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think we fundamentally know &lt;b&gt;why&lt;/b&gt; our brains favor intervals such as this—in fact, it isn’t even clear if animals have opinions about intervals at all—but it seems to be the way it works. We can, however, make a guess why the two pitches sound “similar”. Maybe it is because a sound with frequency $2x$ necessarily also has frequency $x$. This does, however, not reveal why the magic number is $2$, instead of $3$ or something. (But the brain &lt;b&gt;does&lt;/b&gt; favor sounds at frequencies $x$ and $3x$ played simultaneously. This would be a perfect twelfth, and sounds harmonious, but nothing like duplicating a sound)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Western tuning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Western tuning can be constructed from two pieces of information: a single note, and the number of equal intervals we split an octave into. The single note acts like an “origin”, and in Western music we often take&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lawrence Borst</name></author><summary type="html">I see microtonal music as an often dissonant art. This perception owes itself in part to its strangeness, but also to scientific principles that make many types of microtonal music unattractive. For example, imagine a pitch. Play it in your head, and then layer it with a second pitch just slightly above the first. What you’re hearing is a dissonant interval, and we shall go over the reason why that may be.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lagrange interpolation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/15/Lagrange-Interpolation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lagrange interpolation" /><published>2020-11-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/15/Lagrange%20Interpolation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/15/Lagrange-Interpolation.html">&lt;p&gt;To launch this website, let’s begin with the simple but elegant idea of Lagrange interpolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim is to find a polynomial of degree $n$ that passes through $n-1$ points. People educated in linear algebra often can see that this is possible just by setting up the associated system of linear equations. For completeness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If $P(x)=a_{0}+a_{1}x+\cdots+a_{n}x^{n}$ and $P(x_{0})=y_{0}$, $P(x_{1})=y_{1}$,$\cdots$,$P(x_{n-1})=y_{n-1}$ then we have the following system:&lt;/p&gt;

\[y_{0}=a_{0}+a_{1}x_{0}+\cdots+a_{n}x_{0}^{n}\]

\[y_{1}=a_{0}+a_{1}x_{1}+\cdots+a_{n}x_{1}^{n}\]

\[\vdots\]

\[y_{n-1}=a_{0}+a_{1}x_{n-1}+\cdots+a_{n}x_{n-1}^{n}\]

&lt;p&gt;$n$ unknowns and $n$ equations. This we know is solveable. You can solve this by hand for a few points—and a computer will have no trouble with thousands of points—but our aim is to find a closed-form formula for the interpolating polynomial. Looking at this set of equations might not get us anywhere close to solving this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of revealing the trick, I encourage the reader to think about the problem. A good line of reasoning is something like this: “The main difficulty is that when you assume a function $P(x)$ and tweak the coefficients to fit through some point, the polynomial will inevitably slip away from other points.” It is a bit like trying to get rid of a crease on your bedsheets; flattening one part will cause a pinch to pop up elsewhere. So then we might ask ourselves: “Is there a way to treat an individual point without disturbing the rest?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, consider one of the points we’re trying to pass through. If we can associate a polynomial (which is what the question is about) with an individual point that’s “nice” in a way that “does not disturb the others”, we would need a total of $n$ polynomials to address all points. Every polynomial should act in a similar way to its associated point, because no point is “special”. So something should be quite “natural” about this polynomial. It should pass through a point, and as for the others… Well, be equal to $0$ at the others (can you think of anything else?). This is quite a natural thing to do with the other points, and as it turns out, it is easy to find the associated polynomial. Promising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say $P_{i}(x)=0$ at $x=x_{j}$ for all $j \neq i$ and $P_{i}(x_{i})=y_{i}$. By the fundamental theorem of calculus, we have:&lt;/p&gt;

\[P_{i}(x)=C_{i}\prod_{j \neq i} (x - x_{j})\]

&lt;p&gt;For some constant $C_{i}$. Plugging in $P_{i}(x)=y_{i}$ gives $C_{i}=y_{i} / \prod_{j \neq i} (x_{i} - x_{j})$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have tamed the problem in the sense that we can find a polynomial of degree $n-1$ through a given point, that equals $0$ at all the other points. The attempt so far may not lead anywhere—as happens often when you’re tackling a problem for the first time—but some thought reveals that the sum of all these polynomials goes through the points $(y_{0}, x_{0}), (y_{1}, x_{1}),\cdots,(y_{n-1}, x_{n-1})$. Therefore&lt;/p&gt;

\[P(x)=\sum_{i=0}^{n-1}y_{i} \frac{\prod_{j \neq i} (x - x_{j})}{\prod_{j \neq i} (x_{i} - x_{j})}\]

&lt;p&gt;Solves the problem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lawrence Borst</name></author><summary type="html">To launch this website, let’s begin with the simple but elegant idea of Lagrange interpolation.</summary></entry></feed>